[music]
>> The south of China is a veritable maze
of rivers and mists.
The landscape engravings of the Guangxi
province.
Over hundreds of kilometers, the
indentations of the limestone reliefs
impose countless meanders upon the
rivers.
These lands of dream [music] and legend
are the cradle of an ancient art that
jealously guards its mystery.
>> [music]
>> Paintings in red pigments decorate the
rock face, often dozens of meters above
the ground.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Who were these painters of the
impossible?
How did they [music] manage to create
such works?
What was their meaning?
For what religion or god were they
painted?
>> [music]
[music]
>> For more than 2,000 years on the site of
Huashan, we've admired [music] their
startling work from a 180-m high cliff.
Some claim, in fact, [music] that
Huashan means the mountain with
paintings.
Huashan,
the greatest monument [music]
in the rock art world.
From his farm in the Vercors, [music]
archaeologist Jean-Louis Le Quellec
dreams of Washan's mysteries.
CNRS researcher, leading rock art
specialist, and tireless traveler,
Jean-Louis Le Quellec however has never
been to Washan.
He is however eager to go, and not just
for the beauty of these sites, [music]
but because the art in this region of
the world may help him answer a question
that to him is vital.
Why does rock art exist?
>> What is this idea of drawing on a rock
face, on a mountain, on a cliff?
People, animals, signs.
It's a funny idea in fact. Why?
And for whom?
Washan may hold the beginnings of an
answer.
At least in mythological terms.
And it was at a time and a place when
writing existed.
China is also interesting in that it's
one of the places in the world where
writing was invented eons ago.
So we have very ancient texts.
So suddenly, there may be a connection
here. It could at least shed light on
the context. And that's very rare, too.
Nowhere else in the world, virtually, do
we have this kind of thing for such
ancient periods.
>> Mythologies, legends, and even texts
dating back almost 3,000 years.
No other rock art site can boast so many
clues that might enable us to pierce its
mysteries.
Yet the art of Washan is still little
studied by Western researchers.
And it's that, too, that sparks
Jean-Louis curiosity, enough to inspire
some real exploration work.
That's why he and his English friend,
archaeologist Paul Bahn, resolved to
journey to Washan and together explore
the enigmas of its art.
>> [music]
>> Paul and Jean-Louis kept their word.
>> They're making their dream trip to
Washan come true.
To reach Guangxi,
to sail down the Mingjiang,
to find the rocky pyramid of Washan
placed on the river.
What might you feel on such a journey?
Will you find the land of legend
described in the texts? Will you finally
find answers to the questions that have
tormented [music] you for years?
They now must regain terra firma and
approach the reality of the site. First
of all, in the company of Zhu Qiping,
the archaeologist in charge of
conservation on the site, and Grace,
their Chinese interpreter.
They began by observing the painted rock
face from the opposite bank.
>> So, how many paintings do we have here?
>> How many do you have
do you have here?
In the Huashan we have found 1,951
paintings on this site.
>> And so what what is the size? What is
the width and the the height of the of
the panel here?
>> From top to bottom the painted face is
45 m high.
Its total width is 221 m.
We can't see very well from where we
are, but in fact there are lots of
little paintings.
The smallest of them measures only 20
cm.
Most are between 80 cm and 1.6 m.
Lots of paintings are bigger than we
are.
Above all there's this one we can see
there just above the treetops.
The size of the characters is 3.6 m.
I often wonder how they could have
painted people so big. It must be very
difficult.
>> These impressive dimensions make the
great cliff of Huashan an exceptional
work unique in the world.
>> One of the major aspects of course of
Huashan is its absolute monumentality.
This is the biggest rock art panel we
know of anywhere in the world and
clearly this was their intention to make
something really breathtaking, huge, and
impressive.
>> The picture frame is quite simply the
mountain, the whole mountain.
One face of the mountain is the canvas.
All of a sudden it takes on a different
scale.
I could never have imagined what it's
like to be here.
>> It's in a very beautiful landscape with
all these astonishing limestone uh
mountains which you only really get in
Southeast Asia. The river itself is is
very beautiful. You have buffalo on the
on the two banks. You have people
fishing, people farming. And then
Huashan itself, of course, is very
special because it's like a great
triangular space
um which clearly was very special to the
people who who decorated it.
And to suddenly come upon that, and then
as you get closer to start to see these
figures these figures slowly emerging as
you get closer and closer is is really
very very striking.
>> The realistic from those are very high
ones.
>> It's all about the physical impression
because we're tiny compared to this vast
rock face.
You have to lean backwards to see
things.
It really does tower above us.
It's very very high.
So these characters looking down on you
are very impressive.
Although the Huashan mountain is the
most important of this ancient arts
[music] monuments,
map in hand, Paul and Jean-Louis
discover that in fact there are more
than 80 secondary sites spread out along
the region's two rivers, the Minjiang
and the Zuojiang.
On the cliffs at the base of these
rivers, there are dozens of examples.
But a dozen more sites have also been
discovered away from the rivers on
mountains in the jungle.
Originally,
>> [music]
>> the rainforest reigned over these
isolated lands.
Patiently, a rural civilization has
loosened the forest's grip by carving
out an agricultural landscape made of
fields of rice and sugarcane, still one
of the region's main [music] resources.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Here, retracing the course of the river,
main thoroughfare between these
limestone masses,
is like going back in time.
Here, you are light-years away from the
frenzied hustle and bustle of the
country's major cities,
or even in Ningming, the nearest town.
Visitors to Washan must first cross the
perpetual chaos of the factories and
building sites to find a world that is a
world away, all silence and slowness.
If they follow the river's rhythm,
it would be impossible for Paul and
Jean-Louis to reach all the sites and
see everything. On the advice of Zhu
Quping, they decide to target two sites
that are typical of the region,
the sites of Dushan and Gaoshan.
To get there, they take a boat upstream
[music] of Washan, one of these elegant
flat-bottom boats.
Compared to Washan, Dushan has few
decorated [music] panels, but turns out
to be even more dizzying.
There's also something just above the
gray rock, there.
Some red panels.
Little trees on this kind of plateau
here.
They could have gone there to paint, but
even climbing up here
very mysterious. What pushed them to
such acrobatic extremes to reach
improbable heights to paint pictures
that are only visible from afar.
It's often said that for much of rock
art, it was a very strong motivation.
Often it's found in places that are hard
to access.
And here, it takes incredible
motivation. It [clears throat] couldn't
have just happened.
Someone wouldn't come along and think,
"Hey, I'll knock off two or three
paintings here."
It takes long preparation, no doubt.
They probably risked their lives to do
these things.
And why choose this spot specifically?
Finding paintings so high up a cliff
face that seems so inaccessible comes as
a shock.
How were they executed?
This is perhaps the first great mystery
of Huashan art.
Paul and Jean Loic will try to solve it
by questioning one of the leading
experts,
>> [music]
>> archaeologist Qin Shaoniang, who has
devoted a major part of his career to
studying these paintings.
After analysis of all the paintings at
the site,
we assume that there may be various
possibilities.
First of all, for the lower parts,
the painters could have worked from the
terraces just above the river.
The paintings higher up could have been
done at the time of the floods
from boats or from bamboo scaffolding.
The rest we can't explain
because it's impossible to come down on
a rope from the summit of the mountain
and impossible to climb up from the
base.
Bamboo scaffolding is the only plausible
explanation.
Here in the south of China,
there is lots of bamboo.
So, scaffolding techniques are very
elaborate.
Chen Chao-yuan only retained three
theories:
climbing, ropes, and scaffolding.
>> [music]
>> Climbing, why not?
But, how did the artist climber manage
to carry with him the material and
quantity of pigments needed to such
[music] a height? And how did he manage
to paint such big figures while holding
on to the rock face?
Hanging from ropes [music] from the top
of the mountain?
It's a fantasy on all levels.
At Huashan, for example, the angle of
the cliff face would leave the artist
hanging much too far from the surface of
the rock.
The most realistic theory is that of
scaffolding.
It seems reasonable to use bamboo
[music] scaffolding built up from the
ground or down from the tops of the tall
trees.
But, sometimes, even this theory doesn't
totally dispel the mystery.
And as plants like bamboo don't keep,
there's no evidence to back it up.
Whatever the case, what an insane
challenge.
What motivation could be sufficient to
push someone into doing this.
>> [music]
>> Some mystic ritual?
>> It makes you wonder if
this was really part of the
the process of doing this art was to
show, "Look how clever I am. Look how
brave I am. Look how crazy I am, maybe,
to go that high. I can make a painting
up there. Nobody else can go as high as
that." So, it may be a phenomenon of
showing your prowess, showing your
bravery, showing your sheer ability as
an artist. You can go higher than
anybody else. You can reach a place that
would seem impossible to reach, and yet
you can make a fine painting there.
>> The Huashan rock face itself, the
images, the main panel,
the characters are organized like a kind
of human pyramid.
It really looks like people making an
attempt on the summit.
So, there's something that points
towards climbing.
And probably in a quest for immortality,
rising to heaven.
>> Jean-Louis remembers the research he
carried out in France.
The link between these painted figures
and these mountains reminded him of
ancient texts of Chinese mythology and
the illustrations that accompanied them.
>> The fact of using the mountain as a kind
of elevator to immortality
is something that is very present.
We have prints that represent great
sages that were turned into mountains.
And one of the most famous represents
Laozi,
who is considered the founder of Taoism
and therefore an immortal.
So, there are all these traditions that
tell us that the great sages,
when they felt the end was near,
climbed a mountain and arrived at the
summit.
They spread their arms wide.
And when they spread their arms, their
garment,
a large cape,
is transformed into a dress of feathers,
and they fly away and become immortal.
So, the image of Laozi is that of an
immortal, a great immortal sage.
Chinese mythology can give us a few
clues to the popular imagination of the
time, but to delve further, Paul and
Jean Louis need to pick up the
investigation with the figures
themselves, and one simple question,
what do they represent?
Scenes from daily life, moments of real
life,
or something else again?
Here, we're in front of a panel that's
very typical in Huashan.
In the center, there's this big figure
on a dog that seems to be the main
character on the panel.
He's carrying a sword with a circular
pommel,
and also a dagger in his right hand.
He seems to have a small animal on his
head.
And he is standing atop another animal,
enormous this time.
It is clearly the central figure.
The chief of the tribe.
All around, the other characters have
their hands raised.
Many are crouching down or kneeling, as
if venerating,
or as part of a ceremonial dance.
Unlike lots of instances of rock art,
which evoke hunting or harvest scenes,
Huashan paintings represent a ceremony,
a sacred cult.
>> Thus the main panel of Washan
transcribes a grand celebration honoring
warriors armed with swords and sitting
atop animals.
A mysterious cult embraced by an entire
people.
But which people?
We must delve into the intricacies of
Chinese history.
Dating back close to 2500 years, the
Washan paintings seem to have been
carried out in a context that historians
refer to as the Warring States period.
Following countless wars against the
small independent mountain kingdoms,
the Qin Dynasty and then the Han Dynasty
managed to impose their dominance.
In 221, Emperor Qin Shi Huangdi won a
decisive victory that definitively
brought the Washan region under the wing
of what would become the Han Empire.
The Han civilization subsequently
influenced local cultures and the rock
art tradition gradually died out.
The various methods of dating have
confirmed that the paintings were done
before the Han conquest.
Historians agree that they are the work
of an indigenous people,
the Luoyue, who did indeed live in these
mountains 2500 years ago.
Members of a minority called Zhuang
are thought to be descendants of this
people.
Thanks to the Zhuang, the Luoyue legends
are still handed down today.
And Jean-Michel is thrilled to hear Zhu
Quping evoke one of these legends.
It could shed light on the meaning of
the ritual that has been carried out
here for centuries.
The Zhuang worshipped dogs.
According to legend,
back when the Zhuang had no rice,
a genie tried to help them get some rice
to eat.
So, he sent the dog to steal rice from
the god of thunder.
As the dog was their friend,
but forgot to take a sack with him in
which to put the rice.
But as he was clever,
he rolled around in the god's granary,
and the rice stuck to his fur.
Alas,
the god of thunder caught him
and punished him.
But it was a dog with nine tails,
and the god cut off all save one.
The
dog returned to the world of the Zhuang
with just a few grains of rice still
stuck to the only tail that remained.
The Zhuang planted them,
and so originated the rice we eat today.
The legend of the dog who stole the rice
provides a glimpse of one of the cults
depicted at Washan.
It involves the dog and the god of
thunder,
and is a nod to the vital importance of
rice growing.
Do the painted scenes evoke an agrarian
rather than warlike mythology,
divinities rather than combatants?
But Zhu Quping indicates that the
archaeological remains themselves offer
essential information.
For besides the human figures and the
other types of figures are repeated on
all the decorated panels.
They evoke, for instance, bells or
drums, instruments central to the grand
celebration represented.
Zhu Quping describes the stylized
representations that could be those of
drums, concentric circles or circles
bearing a star or with a sun at their
center.
A large number of real drums made of
bronze and dating back 2,500 years were
discovered in the region. Their
similarities with the circular motifs
would seem to confirm the dating of the
paintings and, of course, that they
belong to a culture, that of the Luoyue.
Painted drums and real drums, is this a
new link from which to learn a little
more about the great story of Washan?
The most complete collection of bronze
drums from the province is to be found
in the Nanning Museum of Popular
Traditions.
Paul and Jean-Luc are welcomed by one of
the curators, Liu Wenyi, and Yang
Yangyi, a researcher on his team.
>> The Luoyue, who are responsible for two
major creations,
the Washan paintings and the bronze
drums.
These two creations loomed large in
their daily lives.
At that time,
both drums and paintings were linked to
sacred cults.
They're inseparable, and today they
afford us a glimpse of their customs.
>> A new recurrent figure on the drums
intrigues Paul and Jean-Luc.
>> But I notice on many of the drums here,
there is a very dominant motif, which is
little statuettes of frogs. But we have
not seen real depictions of frogs in the
rock art. So, is there a connection
between the two in that respect?
>> I believe the frogs were deified.
And the posture of characters on the
Huashan paintings evoke a frog.
The Luoyue were a farming people.
To them, the frog was a very important
animal.
Their croaking would herald the rain.
The rain is capital to farmers.
That's why the Luoyue worshipped frogs.
The Zhuang
also have many fables that feature
frogs.
For example,
the frog embodies the son of the god of
thunder.
And croaks that ask for rain.
>> So, we have the sun,
we have the thunder,
we have the frog. She is used to
forecast the weather.
So, all this looks like a kind of
mythology around agriculture.
Is it correct?
>> In fact, the bronze drums are like
boats.
They show us farming scenes.
Scenes from everyday life and all the
importance of a farming people's
relationship with the earth.
>> So, why place the painting so high on
the cliffs if it's related with
agriculture?
>> I think the main reason was that the
Luoyue wanted to glorify these elements.
It was directed to the gods, gods that
the Luoyue would call upon to obtain
help and demonstrate their adoration.
>> These objects and their decoration
represented on the Washan paintings
enable us to admire the art of Luoyue
and seem to confirm the theory of
farming ritual.
Washan art would thus seem to be at the
crossroads between everyday and
spiritual.
Distant heirs to the Luoyue kingdoms,
today the Zhuang are a farming people.
Would meeting the Zhuang minority be
like meeting the creators of the bronze
drums and more especially the authors of
these paintings?
Of the great original story of Washan?
It's hard to shake that idea.
Paul and Jean De Wiquitte visit a small
village not far from Washan along with
Gan Chao Cheng, singer and storyteller
in the Zhuang language.
He helps them to meet a Zhuang family.
Though the meeting may be brief, Jean De
Wiquitte would like to find any traces
of a continuity between the Zhuang today
and their distant ancestors.
>> Yeah.
Um yes, we are the singers of this
village and most importantly
on a song fair.
>> So he sang to her. He sang to her.
>> First they sing to her.
>> [laughter]
>> And because
she's also
sort of fond of him, so they singing
together and uh
>> Right away what is striking is that
Grace, the translator, doesn't
understand Zhuang.
Gong Xiao Zheng must play the
interpreter.
He confirms that the villagers know all
the legends and the ancient songs handed
down in the Zhuang language.
But it's impossible in such a short time
to explore such a vast world.
What isn't undeniable is that the Zhuang
language identifies a people and its
culture.
To me the key connection that is still
present and still evident is the
language.
The language is the main vector of the
tradition.
Which is by definition oral. So that
means the songs.
We're dealing with people who evidently
perpetuate the Zhuang tradition or a
part of the Zhuang tradition.
It's hardly surprising that on such a
quick visit we haven't found the things
we'd have loved to find.
Such as the magnificent story of the
painting's origin.
That would have been rather miraculous,
you have to admit.
With each passing day, Paul and
Jean-Louis feel that despite their
hopes, Huashan will only yield fragments
of its mystery.
They have succeeded in lifting one
corner of the veil, but it would take a
long and thorough investigation to
establish the multi-millennial link to
the Luo Yue.
They have, however, noted that everyone
in the region is affected by the
paintings.
All are impressed by the posture of the
painted characters.
For some,
>> [music]
>> it's the posture of the frog,
the deified animal carved on the bronze
drums.
For others, it is a key action from a
very ancient martial art called Wushu.
Agrarian cult
or warrior cult?
Paul and Jean-Loïc are looking to find
out more about the theory of a warlike
origin, thanks to Gan Ming, chief of
police of Ningming, Washan's neighboring
town.
For the policeman is also, and above
all, mayor of Wushu.
The meeting took place in Ningming
school after a demonstration on a
Chinese scale.
>> So, what what's the connection between
this and the rock art? Because we see he
has this
reproduction of the main panel in
Washan. So, what are the connections
between what we have seen now and the
Washan main panel?
>> Washan Quan
is a sport derived from Wushu,
which was created during the Zhou
Dynasty
between 256
and 145 years BC.
It was handed down from generation to
generation and spread over the whole
territory.
It developed during the lives of our
ancestors when they plowed the fields,
hunted, and grew strong so as to resist
attacks from other tribes.
For more than 2,000 years, Washang Quan
was passed on through words and acts
from previous generations to the next
generations.
Our generation is also taking up the
sport.
At that time, there were no papers, so
our ancestors passed on Washang Wushu by
painting on the rock.
>> They didn't just pass on Wushu, but also
other things.
>> Yes, of course.
>> Could he maybe give us lesson number
one?
>> First lesson.
>> Lesson one.
>> I admit I have some reservations about
the contemporary reading of these
images.
For example, there are two main readings
that people often quote.
One makes an allusion to frogs because
of the position of the characters with
symmetrical arms and legs that might
possibly evoke a frog.
To others, it evokes Wushu,
which is a very ancient combat technique
from this region, different from other
regions Wushu, etc.
Okay, maybe, but it's based on virtually
nothing, just this position.
It just fits into a current reality
where to give meaning to these images.
That's very important as not all the
places in the world where there is rock
art, the local people firstly take an
interest.
And secondly, also try to impart meaning
and consider that meaning very
important, essential even to their own
identity.
>> Paul and Jean will be gradually
understand that in current Chinese
society various accounts inspired by the
paintings coexist.
Agrarian rights or warlike mythologies,
>> [music]
>> it matters not if these interpretations
are incompatible.
The authorities don't hesitate to merge
them together into one big official
story, which is even more useful [music]
as the site is now a candidate for the
UNESCO World Heritage list.
>> Everywhere in hotels, on bath towels,
street lamps, roadside billboards,
we see images borrowed from Huashan
iconography.
>> There's a momentum underway. [music]
It involves a program of major
refurbishment and site development.
Everything is being rescaled for mass
access by tourists as well as to keep
the works [music] safe with, for
example, permanent surveillance by CCTV
and the launch of records programs
[music]
that use the latest technologies.
Paul and Jean will be also [music]
witness a data collection operation on
the Huashan cliff face with the help of
a strange process.
>> So, could you explain us what are you
about to do here? What is this machine?
>> This is a laser 3D scanner.
This technique enables you to take a
three-dimensional 360° record.
>> What's the relation between this machine
and the drone? Are they working
together?
>> The 3D scanner just gives us the relief.
And the drone captures visual
information.
We thus build up a relief panoramic
vision.
In fact, we combine the data from two
different machines.
The two tools don't work together.
But they round each other out for the
final rendering.
The laser beam allows us to map with
millimeter precision the relief of the
painted face.
At the same time, this same face is
filmed in high resolution by a drone.
The images and the scan relief are then
united by a computer application in
order to reconstruct a 3D record with
unprecedented precision.
Paul and Jean-Louis observe the result
on the computer of the young engineer in
charge of the program and under the
curious gaze of Qin Chai Luan.
Around 10 years ago, he carried out an
exhaustive survey of rock art paintings
in [music] the region. But using a quite
different technique.
One based on watercolors, more artistic
than digital.
At the time of the first survey,
an illustrator colleague copied the
paintings from a distance using a zoom
lens.
I was standing by to help with another
telescope.
We compared it as best we could with the
original.
But the dimensions could only be an
estimation.
To the surprise of many, the comparison
reveals far more than a difference in
method.
It allows us to discover the evolution
of Huashan's main panel, or its
degradation to be exact.
>> This is C
>> Jean-Luc asks if it's possible to
compare a small figure he liked on the
two surveys, that of the boat.
>> This This is it.
Yes, this is it.
Uh this is interesting to compare with
the
the old tracing.
>> This part has disappeared from erosion
by the wind and rain.
>> The new technology is is just fantastic
in
in producing more information, more
accurate information.
And also helping you to see the
deterioration that has happened to some
of these [music] panels just in the last
30 years.
>> Jean-Luc is already imagining how
DStretch, the colorimetric analysis
software he's using, could complement
these new scanner techniques.
By playing with the color of the
photographs, DStretch reveals motifs
that overlays or alterations have
rendered almost invisible.
A computer process that augments the
range of new tools available to the
researchers.
Qin Chaoluan then offers to guide Paul
and Jean-Luc to a very beautiful panel
far from [music] the river.
One now, unfortunately, almost
completely erased.
Maybe Jean-Luc's process will enable
them to rediscover the panel.
>> [music]
>> Okay. Okay. Okay.
>> The damp mist soaked the heights of the
Phu Sui County.
The drizzle turns to rain when the
little group that has formed around Paul
and Jean-Loïc attempts to clear a path
through to the site of Balai.
Chinchai Luang's panel is no more than
100 m away, but the forest stands as a
last line of defense.
>> Thank you.
>> Obviously,
a lot of detail has been lost.
But it's pretty monumental in size.
It must have been made to be seen from
far away, and we can guess that they
reached that level.
>> By standing on that little ledge there.
>> Yeah, but even from there, they couldn't
have reached.
They couldn't have done the bird.
>> In fact,
it isn't very visible, especially
because the rock is very deformed, and
there are a lot of cupules, so it
affects visibility.
But here, I think with the DStretch, we
could get a very good result, and we'll
make it all visible.
>> As expected, the main panel reveals more
than can actually be seen.
One of the most eloquent testimonies to
Washan art is fast disappearing.
But Chinchai Luang's intuition was
right.
What Paul and Jean-Loïc believed they
spotted will be revived by the photos
thanks to DStretch,
even revealing details invisible to the
naked eye.
The group discovers other paintings by
descending to a natural rock shelter.
The key figures of Huashan art are all
present.
Characters with typical posture and
drawing style, drums and dogs. Still the
same images even several kilometers from
the river.
>> What I really like in this example is
that not only are we sheltered from the
rain, but we can really get close, very
close to the figures, much more so than
that Huashan.
They came up to this level, so we can
really see the size and the technique of
these paintings.
>> It's the first time we've been at the
same height as the paintings.
>> On top of that,
it's an example of rock art that is
still used in current belief systems.
We can see the offerings and the candles
and so on, and so it continues to play a
role in the world today.
>> So, this way of worshipping the
painting, is it something new? Or can we
consider that since the beginning the
paintings were worshipped in some way,
not exactly in the same way, but we
don't know how, but
can we imagine that?
>> There are lots of different rituals.
To us,
the paintings reflect a ceremony.
They're like a camera that records the
moments of a ceremony.
The offerings to the gods and the
ancestors,
the dances, etc.
It's a easy to get finding.
>> The conversation over, Qin Cai Lu Wan
goes off to one side and begins a ritual
that Paul and Jean-Louis don't expect at
all from a scientist.
In the Huashan region, Paul and
Jean-Louis witness the use of an ancient
art as a source of new beliefs.
Though the original meaning is to a
great extent lost, the sanctity of the
paintings persists [music] through the
ages.
Today, the Zhuang minority sees in these
paintings the illustration of a founding
myth,
even adopting it as an identifying
symbol.
One that the authorities eagerly promote
as long as its cultural value serves
Chinese grandeur.
>> [music]
>> And as every myth needs a hero,
here are two.
Huashan is celebrating the return of the
Zhu brothers.
Native to the region, [music] the Zhu
brothers are painters and artists now
settled in Chicago and world-renowned.
They are welcomed like rockstars because
even the origin of their work is closely
linked to the art of Huashan.
In 2011, Barack Obama commissioned them
to do a painting to be presented to the
Chinese president on an official visit
to the United States.
Today, the Zhu brothers are famous media
darlings.
They willingly lend themselves to the
game of Chinese cultural affirmation.
>> I think is that this
this thing, we believe this thing is a
ancient this is a ancient uh rock
painting is created by the Zhuang
minority.
And then that's why we are they're very
>> You feel maybe
>> uh from your blood you feel uh
connected.
>> Maybe this painting this kind of
painting will provide our some kind of
spirit.
Like
>> What
>> is a spirit for the contemporary art?
What's the spirit for
like the painting the new language? And
then you can, you know, you're always
looking for.
And this thing
we feel
is something very basic very basic there
because of our contemporary art is
something
you need something very strong but very
silent but very powerful and basic.
>> [music]
[singing]
[music]
>> That day Paul and Jean-Luc are not in
Washan to meet the Zhu brothers.
But they know their work and decide to
round off their trip by visiting the
Nanning Museum of Contemporary Art.
There they find their large works
and look for links with Washan art.
>> There's different things in each section
but the only real inspiration I can see
from
from the Washan rock art of these two
human figures here
and possibly a drum underneath.
But clearly this is not the main focus
of this painting. It's just it seems to
be an incidental inspiration.
>> I find it interesting that on this
painting
the The elements to those of the
original Washan paintings
is at the center.
At the same time, that's the least
visible part. And what emerges from afar
is their current art, which is inspired
by these images, but which has distanced
itself considerably.
>> The feeling is liberty.
Because everything is by feeling and
those those guy when they're in I don't
know like how many thousand years ago
when they paint those painting number
one they will not have a drawing.
They don't They don't have a drawing.
They don't have a measurement. And maybe
they have a very basic color. And then
they don't uh think the people either
like it or not.
Yeah, they just feel this is
they create something really powerful
and like holy. I think kind of the
little bit we like to do the
>> like
related to just like a great master.
They're very confident of what they do.
Yeah.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The fact that the Zou brothers have
somehow appropriated Washan art
is to me all part of the same process or
the same phenomenon.
As the people who interpret the Washan
anthropomorph
as the ancestor of the Wushu martial art
it's part of the same dynamic as people
reinterpreting the images as gods or as
spirits before which even now we offer
prayers.
What seems important to me is that in
the end this art is still alive in one
way or another, that totally different
people each give it a particular
meaning, which in a way allows it to
keep living.
For Paul and Jean De Week, this first
exploration has allowed them to gather
certain clues from which to elucidate
the meaning of the spectacular images of
Huashan.
But only clues.
Patient research is required,
particularly to the [music] Zhuang
people, to obtain anything more.
After the trip, the most unexpected
[music] part will doubtless be seeing
the key role played by this ancient art
in contemporary society.
Each era, [music]
each human community feels the need to
recreate its own story from those lost
in the meanders of a too distant past.
[music]
A process upon which the researchers'
hard work will shed light.
The fact that Huashan art has become
[music] the rallying point for a whole
community means that its fascination
still works.
The mystery of its beautiful, crazy
gesture remains.
And it inspires us.
It passes on some of its boldness, even
in a society like Chinese [music]
society, where evolution may sometimes
appear like a forced march,
an ancient art like that of Huashan will
survive the vagaries of history and will
never be forgotten. [music]
>> Ooh.